and then they come back to us and
they're like
you know there are like 50 million
people named khalid al-masri this is not
the guy you're looking for
and they release him
but when he comes out of egypt he's got
a beard down to his waist he's holding a
copy of the quran and he told a reporter
all he wants to do now is kill americans
because that's what we did to him right
we do this kind of thing all the time
well didn't we sort of create bin
laden's ideology against america i'm
glad that you put it that way
the answer to that question is yes we
did
we didn't create bin laden there's this
there's this misconception that bin
laden was
one of the afghan mujahideen that we had
funded during the war against the
soviets he wasn't he didn't arrive in
um in afghanistan until after the
soviets had departed
but in terms of that ideology absolutely
yes we created that group what we did is
we had such an obsession with communism
well into the late 80s
that it was you know the policy was to
defeat the russians at all costs right
and one of the things that we did to
defeat the russians
was to provide
stinger missiles to the afghan
mujahideen
and it was the missile that that turned
the war around because all of a sudden
you know from a shoulder launcher you
can take down a russian plane a russian
helicopter we just decimated the russian
military that way
and what we did is we we radicalized
these guys
and then the russians are gone
and
they're still radical
and then what do we do then we have
september 11th right
jesus um do you think
that
i mean obviously
i know your stance on you know all these
crazy these [__] torture techniques
that we used to use like waterboarding
and
and all of these things but do you think
that waterboarding has ever been an
effective technique no never never
never it's meant to punish
not not to collect information
i'll tell you
you know how i feel about the fbi
it's hard for me to compliment the fbi
but if there's one thing that the fbi is
good at it's interrogation
they've been doing it since the
nuremberg trials right in 45-46
and what they do it's not sexy and it's
not something you see in the movies
but they establish a rapport with a
subject they're kind to the subject
instead of beating him and electrocuting
him and you know throwing ice water on
him
they offer him a cigarette or an orange
or a date or you know
paper to write to his parents or
whatever
and over the course of time and usually
it's only a few weeks
the subject will open up and provide
information see this is this is the post
script to the abazo beta uh capture
story
abso beta was sent to the secret site
and because i'm going to say it for the
third time because 911 was an open
criminal investigation
the primacy was given to the fbi that
drove the cia crazy
we wanted primacy this was our operation
but the fbi specifically an fbi agent by
the name of ali soufan
began to interrogate abu zabeda and what
he did is we waited until he was
recovered from the gunshots
and um
and ali sat across a table from him
and
talked
and like i say he'd offer him a
cigarette
offer him
an apple or a cup of tea or something
and over the course of weeks abuza beta
began to speak now abzobeda told us two
things that were absolutely critically
important number one we didn't have any
idea what the al qaeda
wiring diagram looked like
no idea we knew bin laden was the boss
and zoihedi was the
underboss for lack of a better term and
that was it we didn't know anything else
we knew that there's al qaeda you know
in rome there's al qaeda in jakarta al
qaeda and mexico city
but we didn't we didn't know who or how
or
how they reported back to bin laden we
didn't know anything so ali said and i'm
just going to use this as an example
if you're going to do an attack
in
dusseldorf
how would you do that
and abuse beta said well i know this guy
muhammad and here's his phone number
he's in dusseldorf and muhammad's got a
friend abdullah and here's abdullah's
phone number abdullah has access to
weapons
and i was talking to abdullah one time
and he told me about this guy rashid and
here's rashid's number
and russia knows explosives he can build
bombs so we can call the germans and say
hey you have a problem in dusseldorf and
here are the guys you need to raid and
then they raid the the apartments and
they grab these guys so we we didn't
know any of that stuff until abu
zubaydah started telling ali soofan
wow the other thing that abu zubaydah
told us about and this was
one of the most important things that we
learned through the course of the
so-called war on terror
we knew that there was a very bad guy
out there
who went by the nom daguerre mukhtar
right we knew this was a bad bad guy who
in 1996
had
conceptualized this operation called the
bojinka plan have you ever heard of
boogie no
so
this was a plan to
hijack
14 747s
leaving from manila airport
and fly all 14 of them into buildings up
and down the west coast of the united
states
it was accidentally broken up by the
philippine police
and all we knew was that the mastermind
was this guy mukhtar and he had escaped
so we knew and this was like a
this was a
teaching point at the cia like we really
lucked out with this one because we
didn't know anything about it
but the philippine
filipino police stumbled on it the guy
got away but here's the plan
we know that al qaeda is going to use
airliners as weapons right so we knew
that in 1996 they wanted to use planes
as weapons
but we didn't know who muktar was
so
ali's like you keep talking about this
muktar
who is he
and abu veda smiles and he said you
don't know mukhtar
and he said well we know that there is a
guy muktar and that he's a bad guy
he's the operational leader of al qaeda
and he said sure who is he he goes
khalid sheikh muhammad
we never heard that name before
we didn't have any idea who khalid
muhammad was
but you know what two months later he's
in custody
and what we did when we when we captured
him we captured him in an al-qaeda safe
house in rawalpindi
um
we walked him past abu zubaydah's cell
so that they could see each other
and abu zubaydah immediately burst into
tears
why did he burst into tears because he
was a true believer
and it was his information that allowed
us to capture khalid muhammad
wow
he ratted him out wow
that's so [__] wild
so [__] wild
um
after you went
to
after you
let's go back or let's jump jump forward
in time
when uh
you originally went on what was it abc
yeah and you spoke out against the the
torture program
what was like the sequence of events to
you getting from going from there to
being actually prosecuted and getting
sent to prison right
so you know i wish i could say that
that my
intention that day was
was purely
patriotic
it actually wasn't
i got a call from brian ross at abc news
and he said
that he had a source
who said that i had tortured abu zabeda
i said that was absolutely untrue i said
i was the only person who was kind to
abu zubaydah i've never laid a hand on
abu zubaydah or on any other prisoner i
said your source is either mistaken or
he's a liar
well he says you're welcome to come on
the show and defend yourself
which i had i had never spoken to an
inter to a journalist before i i didn't
know that was an old reporter's trick
oh he was just lying
uh he said that that's what he had heard
so he did have a real source yeah
so i said i'll think about it
well a couple of days later
the president's giving a
a press conference
one of the reporters asked him about
torture what about these reports that
the cia is torturing people and he looks
in the camera and he says
we do not torture
like that and is this bush bush
i was sitting on the couch watching this
with my wife and i looked at her and i
said he is a bald-faced liar he's
looking the american people in the eye
and he's lying to us
a couple of days after that it's a
friday and he's walking from the south
portico of the white house to the
helicopter to go to camp david and a
reporter shouts a question about torture
again and he stops and he turns and he
says well if there is torture it's a
rogue cia officer
and i looked at my wife and i said
they're gonna try to pin this on me
because they were mad that i was the
only one who spoke out
they're gonna pin this on me
oh this is after you went on abc he said
this no this is before two days before
okay so the guy from abc called you the
journalist called you said this and then
you saw the president yes on tv so
i realized brian ross was telling me the
truth that he did have a source
who said that i had tortured up as a
beta because that was the plan
they were going to say look everybody
knows that we're torturing prisoners
let's pin it on this [__] he's the
one who would never shut up about it
so i said to my wife you were the
humanitarian and i was the human rights
guy
so i called brian ross i said i'll give
you your interview
and i decided in the days leading up to
that interview that whatever he asked me
i was going to tell the truth
and so i said three things in that
interview that just
completely changed the course of the
rest of my life
i said that the cia was torturing its
prisoners
i said that torture was official u.s
government policy it was not the result
of a rogue
and i said that the policy had been
personally approved by the president
himself
the president's a liar
and so whoa as you can imagine
within 24 hours the cia filed what's
called a crimes report against me with
the justice department saying that i had
revealed classified information
my attorney i hired an attorney of
course and my attorney said you got him
on speed dial the second you walked out
of that studio
you can't classify a crime
so
you can't classify a crime yeah they
said he released classified information
torture's illegal and so by virtue of
its illegality it's unclassified
yeah but is it illegal if it's not in
our country it's how do you define if
it's illegal
no the law is crystal clear it can't be
done by an american or any person acting
on behalf of an american
that's what the law says
okay yeah so the fbi investigated me for
a year from december of 2007 until
december of 2008
and in december of 2008 they sent my
lawyer a letter called a declination
letter
saying that they were declining to
prosecute me and then one of the fbi
agents said this was the worst kept
secret in washington everybody knew the
cia was torturing its prisoners
like everybody at the fbi talked about
it and when they started torturing obazo
beta every fbi officer at the secret
site left the country they didn't want
to be in the same country
while it was happening
that's how
wrong they knew it was
so
they dropped the charges my wife and i
went out to dinner that night to
celebrate
three weeks later
barack obama becomes president and john
brennan becomes well first he was named
cia director but then
um they withdrew the nomination he
became the deputy national security
adviser for counterterrorism well john
and i
have always hated each other and he was
one of the founders of the torture
program
so
barack obama becomes president january
the 20th 2009
john brennan asks the justice department
to secretly reopen the case against me
and they investigated me for three more
years until january of 2012.
i had no idea that my phones were tapped
i had no idea that my emails were being
intercepted
i had no idea that it was being followed
by teams of fbi agents
and then on
january
2012 i was arrested
charged with
three counts of espionage
one count of
violating the
uh what was it called the intelligence
identities protection act of 1982
and one count of making a false
statement we were never clear on what
the false statement was supposed to have
been
um
in the end
i hadn't committed espionage just like
tom drake hadn't committed espionage and
ed snowden hasn't committed espionage
and julian assange hasn't committed
espionage so in my case they dropped all
three of those charges
i took a plea to violating the
intelligence identities protection act
and they dropped the false statements
charge
so i had been facing 45 years in prison
and i ended up getting 23 months
wow and i'll tell you i turned down the
23 months they made their best and final
offer right
30 months you do 23.
my wife and i stayed up literally all
night talking about what we should do
and i'm like i'm innocent
i can't take a plea to something that i
didn't do and i had this idea that you
know once i get in front of a jury
they're going to realize how ridiculous
this is they're going to realize that i
was targeted because of my position on
human rights
and so i emailed my lawyers it was six
o'clock in the morning and i said we've
been up all night we decided i'm going
to turn down the best and final
one of the attorneys calls me back
immediately and he says put on a pot of
coffee we're on our way over
so i had 11 lawyers so three of them
come and i mean these are like a list
nationally known the greatest criminal
defense attorneys in washington a
thousand dollars an hour 10 years ago
so
they get to the
house and they each had sort of
different roles one was sort of the the
day-to-day guy
one was this southern gentleman in the
two thousand dollar suit who was nice to
everybody and then one was just an ass
kicker right and i i liked and trusted
him the most
so they're saying look john you're
making a big mistake here
and i said i'm innocent well be that as
it may you know you really should think
about this deal and then the ass kicker
pulls me aside he gets right in my face
and he says you know what your problem
is your problem is you think this is
about justice and it's not about justice
it's about mitigating damage take the
[__] deal
and i thought
see he knows better than i do
i can't win
i
my best friend's wife
keep this
it's linear my best friend's wife has an
uncle
who was o.j simpson's jury consultant
and it wasn't just oj he did
michael patrick smith patrick michael
smith whatever his name was the kennedy
kid
um that got charged with rape he did
george zimmerman
he did does all these big big cases so
because he's
the uncle of my best friend's wife he
agreed to help me for free
so we get him top secret security
clearance from justice he comes up he he
reads all 15 000 pages of classified
documents in my case with this big
meeting i couldn't even meet with my
attorneys at their office we had to meet
at the justice department's conference
room because it was
classified wow yeah awful
so
he said to me look
if we were in any other district in
america
i'd say let's go for it we're going to
win
but the eastern district of virginia the
espionage court
your jury is going to be made up of
people from the cia the pentagon the fbi
the department of homeland security and
a dozen different intelligence
contractors you don't have a prayer
take the deal
so i took the deal
i said to the lead attorney afterwards
if if i hadn't taken the deal
realistically what was i looking at and
he said 12 to 18 years
wow yeah
[__] man it's a joke that everybody in
prison is innocent
one of the things that i learned is
there are a lot of innocent people in
prison oh yeah oh yeah a lot
yeah that's one of the big things about
um i've had a couple lawyers on here or
one in fact a friend of mine who's a
lawyer who represents a lot of people
that get go on death row and he said one
of the biggest issues
um the biggest problems with death row
whether
regardless of what your moral stance is
on it is that they get it wrong a lot a
lot
yes it's been proven yeah like how many
hundreds of people have been exonerated
thanks to dna evidence right it's
[__] unbelievable how often it
happens
this lead attorney that i told you about
the mean one
um he's so rich and has been an attorney
for so long that he doesn't anymore take
like new cases he has people working for
him to do that what he does is he only
does death penalty appeals
that's it really uh-huh
because he said he wants to you know
public service and give back and all
this stuff
he's done 13 death penalty appeals and
he's won all 13 of them
you should see his office what's his
name uh mark mcdougall mark mcdougall
guy's a giant
you go into his sounds like a really
good attorney yeah yeah really really
great attorney at aiken gump and strauss
one of the most important law firms in
the world wow you go into his office and
it's like a museum of awards from every
civil liberties organization in america
you know from the end of naacp to the
brennan center for justice and that's
incredible for all these
these appeals that he's won the guy's a
genius what was it like being
a guy like yourself who's been overseas
seeing all this stuff been in these gun
fights
captured terrorists and then and then
going into prison like yeah what was
that like for you in the beginning then
how did you adapt it was so shocking i
actually wrote a book about it that won
two literary awards i i wrote doing time
like a spy how the cia taught me to
survive and thrive in prison
um
at sentencing my attorneys asked the
judge to send me to a minimum security
work camp
um minimum security
there are no bars on the windows they
don't lock the door you're free to come
and go as you please you're on your
honor not to abscond most everybody
works in town there's a little college
in town
and so the prosecution had no
objection so she you know orders that i
go to uh minimum security work camp
and the funny thing is too
you know you see on
on uh law and order for example when
somebody's guilty
um
right there in the courtroom they they
take them away in cuffs and yeah right
that's that's not how they do i mean
they if you're a really bad guy they do
but what they do is they say okay on
you're going to get a letter from the
bureau of prisons and the letter is
going to tell you the day and the time
that you have to turn yourself in
so they they sent me a letter and they
said come to the prison on february 28th
no later than 11 am
and turn yourself in
so i get in the car with two of my
attorneys my cousin his son and a
documentary film crew and we drive up to
the prison and it's weird you just knock
on the door
and you're like hi i'm john kiriakou i'm
here to turn myself in
and the guy's like
i went to the camp and the guy's like
you got to go across the street to the
prison they process you there and then
they walk you back over here i said okay
so i go across the street to the actual
prison it's got to be so hard it you're
in shock
so it's like your your brain won't even
really process it you're doing it but
you're not
processing it you're not thinking about
it right maybe we should go uh go get
some mcdonald's first we did that
did you yeah
i said let's go to mcdonald's that's so
funny that's what i just randomly
thought of yeah we all went to
mcdonald's
and so i i go to the prison
across the street camps are always
across the street from a higher security
prison or penitentiary so when there's a
riot the guys at the camp can go across
to the prison and do the cooking and the
laundry and the you know mopping while
everybody's on lockdown right
so
i go across the street to the prison i
said i'm john kiriakou here to turn
myself in the guy's like okay just walk
through the metal detector and i walked
through the metal detector
and then he said okay let's uh let's go
we we walk out and instead of going
across street to the camp he starts
leading me around to the back of the
prison and i said no no
i'm supposed to be at the camp across
the street and he goes
not according to my paperwork you're not
and i said what do you mean
he said you're going to prison my friend
like with the guard towers
and the razor wire yeah
the double fences and the razor wire
and i told myself
take it easy
there's nothing you can do
if you raise a stink they're gonna put
you in solitary so i didn't say anything
so
he takes me to this processing area
um
and they
they
give you a uniform
and
a sheet and a pillow and a roll of
toilet paper
and a bath towel right this little stack
of stuff right
and they take your picture for a badge
and
the guy just says follow me i'm sitting
there for 40 minutes
finally the guy says follow me and he
takes me to a cell
and he says that bunk's yours
and then as he's walking out he turns
around he says by the way
if anybody walks into your cell
uninvited that's an act of aggression
and he walks away i'm like what the [__]
is that supposed to mean
i've been here 40 minutes now i'm gonna
get my ass kicked
right
so i'm sitting there and i'm thinking
you have lived in far worse places than
loreto pennsylvania
right
like there's nobody in this prison
more dangerous than the people i've been
working with and i'm including my former
colleagues in that
so i thought you're trained for this you
can handle this
just do what the cia trained you to do
sure enough two guys walk in
just walk in
and i
jumped up out of my seat and i put my
fists up and i go what the [__] do you
want right i'm trying to be as tough as
i can
one of them says take it easy now the
one had this enormous swastika tattooed
on his neck it took up the entire
front of his neck right wow and the
other one had [__] you tattooed on his
eyelids
so every time he blinked it said [__]
you
so i'm standing there with my fists up
he goes are you the new are you the new
guy and i go yeah
and he goes
are you a [__]
and i go no
he goes are you a rat
and i said no i'm not a rat i didn't
have anybody else in my case
and he goes are you a chomo
i go i don't know what that word means
he goes chomo child molester i go no i'm
not a [__] child molester
and he goes okay you can sit with the
aryans in the cafeteria
and i go oh
okay thanks
and i'm thinking
okay so i'm with the aryans now great
so they walk out
not too long after
this black guy walks in and i mean this
guy was just
200 pounds of knotted rippling muscle
right and he's holding a newspaper so he
walks in and he's huge he walks in and i
jump up again i go what do you want
and he goes take it easy and very gently
he hands me the paper and it's the
nation of islam newspaper
and you know in prison the nation of
islam isn't a religion so much as it's a
a gang
right
there's an article about me on the front
of this newspaper
and louis farrakhan of all freaking
people calls me a hero of the muslim
people for standing up for muslim human
rights
so he says i just wanted to tell you
you're not going to have any trouble
with us
and i said okay appreciate it
so he walks away
um it turned out that four of my five
cellmates
were members of um
mexican drug cartels
like all of them nortenos burachos
mexican mafia
these were bad
bad dudes
one of them says to me one day are you
educated and i said yeah
he said could you write my appeal i said
i'm not a lawyer he goes yeah but you
said you're educated i said yeah sure
i'll write your appeal how hard could it
be
half the lawyers i know are you know
dopes anyway yeah
so i wrote his appeal he was totally
guilty he wasn't going to get out but
everybody writes an appeal
so
um he told all the other mexicans
that
i wrote his appeal and that i didn't
charge him anything
it never even occurred to me to charge
him anything
the currency in prison is bags of uh
mackerel right a batgirl yeah okay like
one of these
silver foil bags of mackerel you know
you see the tuna in the grocery store
like a bag of tuna
yeah but mackerel costs one dollar at
the commissary so
everything is in you buy i can't believe
i'm surprised they actually have
mackerel yeah it's disgusting
smells just too high heaven
yeah
but uh anyway so the mexicans left me
alone and then
finally
and this sort of set the tone for the
rest of my time in prison
um
my brother my brother called me right
before i left for prison and i he said
listen you're going to you're going to
fci loretto i got to tell you he goes
there's a guy there
that you really need to stay away from
his name is
i'm not going to say his name
um he's the boss of the gambino family
right
and you know the gambinos are one of the
five families
this guy was in
on 18 murder charges
right
he's the one who replaced john gotti
when gotti was pinched so
he's like stay away from me he's a very
bad dangerous guy
well when i got there i would see him
walking around the yard he was he was
tiny he was like five foot four but
surrounded by these gigantic bodyguards
like half a dozen of them
so i'm sitting in my cell one day i'm
reading the newspaper
and
i see movement out of the corner of my
eye so i turn
and look and it's one of the bodyguards
we used to call him stupid tony because
his eyes were crossed
it's awful
so it's stupid tony and he goes he goes
hey was he actually stupid yeah he was
really stupid yeah yeah guy was going
nowhere in life he goes hey the boss
wants to see you and i go he wants to
see me
and he goes yeah let's go like that
so i jump up thinking [__]
like i've avoided this guy for four
months
and now he's summoning me
so we go all the way to the other side
of the prison
we go to his room
and it's full of guys
hangers on
wannabes
the guy
the boss
is sitting in a chair
there's another guy on his knees
clipping the boss's toenails
utterly disgusting
and then when he finishes
the boss gets up
brushes his teeth there's a little sink
there he brushes his teeth and he spits
and the spit goes all around the sink
right well right behind him there's a
guy sleeping on the top bunk of the bed
and he punches the bed and he goes hey
get up clean his [__] up he says
the guy says you got it boss he jumps
out of bed cleans up all the spit well
i'm standing in the doorway this whole
time
so i go
excuse me
did you want to see me
he goes sit down
so i go and sit down and i'm like
practically shaking i'm so nervous
and he goes you the cia guy
and i said i am
you write a book
i said i did your book do good
i said actually i did very well i made
number five on the new york times best
sellers list
and he goes
you're gonna write my book
and i said oh
is that what this is
what do you have in mind
he goes i'm gonna tell you stories
and you're gonna write my book
i said okay well let's think about this
for a minute you know
i said most of the books of this
genre
uh are written by rats
and i said
they spend the first half of the book
talking about all the cool things they
did and the second half of the book they
try to justify why they turned rat
and i said you're definitely not a rat
and you probably shouldn't talk about
the cool things you've done
and he looks at me and he nods and he
goes
hadn't thought of that
never mind
but from that day
i was invited to every italian dinner
they had a crooked guard on payroll he
would bring us
pork loin
and wine for the marsala sauce and fresh
mushrooms and tomatoes and all the pasta
we needed from the kitchen and i gained
30 pounds in prison holy [__] i gained
30 pounds in prison
and then
we actually stayed in touch
afterwards
um is he still in there no he's out
which leads me to another story
i had been out for
three years
and
around 7 30 one evening my doorbell
rings
and my youngest i have five kids but my
youngest was little at the time he was
like four
busy guy yeah i can't keep my hands to
my mind
so he runs the door and he opens the
door before i can get there and i hear
this sugary sweet voice and he goes hi
is your daddy home
and i thought you [__]
so i go to the door and i said may i
help you i was like actively rude and
it's not my nature to be rude
the guy goes hi mr kiriakou i'm special
agent uh smith with the fbi and this is
my colleague special agent jones and i
said you guys have balls coming here you
know i'm represented by council
and he goes
oh no mr kiriakou it's not about your
case um you see uh it's about another
issue
we know that when you were at loretto
you were friends with uh peter the
rabbit
i said so
well you know
pete got out he's home now i said yeah
good for pete
well uh mr kiriakou um
we have reason to believe that he's
that pete's taken over leadership of the
gambino crime family
and i go
and you want me to rat out a five
family's boss
get off my property
and i closed the door i called my
attorney
he called me back 20 minutes later and
he's like i don't know what they were
thinking but they're not going to bother
you again jesus christ man
that's [__] terrifying because even
if you don't rat them out yeah these
guys will probably use your name exactly
to get this guy exactly and that not
only implicates you imitate your whole
family he called me
oh i'm gonna say
three three it is it's exactly the mob
boss guy yeah the mob boss he called me
three years ago and he said
hey he goes anthony's out anthony was
this guy
he was also a gambino yeah that we
really liked i liked anthony
he was the last one of our group of
friends to be released
and uh
anthony was also the last one to be
transferred to our prison from a maximum
security penitentiary to a medium to a
low okay so i was sitting at the
baseball field
uh in out in the yard sitting with him
when he first arrived
and
poor anthony i mean he was dumb he was
nice but dumb as a stone
and i said to him so anthony
um you mind if i ask you
uh
how much time you have he goes i got 20.
i go 20 years
and he goes yeah i got a long one i said
oh man i'm sorry to hear that you mind
if i ask you what did you what did you
do
and he goes
my crime was
organized in nature
i said right i got it he goes yeah
my victim found himself uh
[Music]
on fire
i said right
yeah
20 years
jesus christ
and he's out now he's out now so is it
part of like a conspiracy case or a
rodriko case yeah they were all all of
them in on rico cases all of them oh my
god yeah yeah rico is real
that shit's crazy so anthony got out any
and the boss called me and he's like hey
we're all getting together in atlantic
city all expenses paid i said cool you
went i went
great fbi is there with their cameras
they're all giving them the finger and
stuff really
and then
you know i i wanted to like i'd never
been to atlantic city before even though
it's two hours away from my house i'd
never been
and i've always heard just terrible
things about it so i wanted to go out
and explore a little bit
so we all pile into these cars and
they're like now we're going to go
you got a gps put this address in your
gps
i said okay i put it in we go it's it's
some run down beat up house i said
what is this supposed to be
this is anthony scarfo's house
he was the boss
okay so what the [__] are we doing here
we're gonna pay respects
i said you guys are like the most boring
travel companions in the world
i want to go what are they going to do
to pay respects we're just sitting out
there oogling at it
[Music]
that's so weird man i you know i've had
a couple you know people who went to
prison under rico charges being involved
with the gambino crime family and and uh
different italian
you know mafia groups and
one thing that's consistent that
they all say to me
is that there's this culture of being
like of anti-rat culture like you can't
be right yeah and they're all rats
they're all rats they're all rats all of
them it was crazy i'll tell you another
thing that was odd it's all about honor
and respect right
so on the one hand
uh we're all standing in the in one of
their cells one day we had dinner right
everybody's sitting around with these
giant bowls heaping bowls of pasta
[Music]
and one of the low-level guys walks in
and he's got like his arms are full of
candy bars
so he starts handing out these candy
bars hershey's bars and snickers bars
and the boss says where the [__] do you
get this and he said uh i broke into a
chomo's locker and i took all of his
[__]
and the boss gets up he goes you put all
this [__] back and you tell him you're
sorry
and everybody stops and looks and the
guy goes but he's a chomo they're the
lowest of the lowest right
he goes if you're going to shake down
ochomo
you do it to his face and you say chomo
open your locker and give me all your
[__] you don't do it behind his back
right now give him all his [__] back
and he did
so after
you did 24 months in prison what was it
like getting out of prison oh you know
getting out was much more stressful than
anybody will tell you
home confinement house arrest is
far worse than prison i'd rather have
just stayed in prison
because with home confinement
you literally cannot leave the four
walls of your house if you step outside
on the front stoop or on the back porch
you're violated you go back to prison
again
and so you go stir crazy you can't do
anything and they've got these
restrictions on you they call you 24
hours a day to make sure that you're
that you're there you haven't run off or
you didn't go out right partying or
whatever constant drug tests i'm like
you guys i've never even smoked weed in
my life i'm happy to waste as much as
your of your time and the government's
money as possible but this kind of
pisses me off now isn't that so stupid
that a lot of people who get arrested
and go to prison for non-drug related
charges they get it's all about drug
testing ridiculous
so it's it's far more stressful
uh coming out of prison see you think
you can step back into your life again
and and you can't that's just not
possible it'll never be possible your
life will never be the same i'm never
going to work for the government again
and you know after i left the cia i went
to the i was the the chief investigator
on the senate foreign relations
committee the highest profile most
prestigious committee on all of capitol
hill
i'm i'm never going to do work like that
again never
so stripped you of your of your entire
pension yeah they took my pension i'm
gonna have to work till the day i die
unless i get a presidential pardon
which is unlikely
now are you still like being shackled
down hard by these restrictions no um in
fact i i was supposed to have three
years of restrictions after i got home
and they lifted them after two oh okay
yeah well that's nice they definitely
don't make it easy when you get out to
get back on your feet and get a job no
in fact i had an offer to be a senior
fellow at a think tank in washington uh
the institute for policy studies it's
the oldest uh progressive think tank in
washington and they wanted me to do
prison reform and sentencing reform
issues and the bureau of prisons
denied me they denied me permission to
take the job and i said listen you guys
are up my ass about getting a job i
finally get a good job and you tell me
that i can't do it they said it would be
inappropriate for you to comment on
prison reform issues
and i said you know what wow i'm gonna
take the job and if you violate me i'll
let you talk to the washington post
about why you violated me
and i took the job and they backed off
no [__]
i got into two incidents with them one
was on that job and those people treated
me like a king at the institute for
policy studies
the other thing was
they make you take these classes
mandatory classes if you don't take the
class you go back to prison
okay
mandatory how to write a resume
i know how to write a resume
how to balance a checkbook thank you i
know how to balance a checkbook
suicide prevention i go don't you think
you should give that before you go to
prison
instead of when you get home
so it was all these stupid um
uh how to kick your drug and alcohol
habit i don't have a drug and alcohol
habit
so i didn't i never signed up for these
classes
i get a call from them one day they said
kiriakou get in here immediately
so
they wouldn't let me drive so i had to
take i had to walk to the metro
which was you know 20 minutes then i'd
take the metro to capitol hill then i
have to get on a bus
and then take the bus to alabama avenue
and take another bus to the to the
halfway house and then walk three more
blocks through the most dangerous block
in the most dangerous neighborhood in
washington took me two hours to go seven
and a half miles right as the crow flies
so i go there and it's everybody it's
the head of the halfway house the deputy
director the case manager a
representative from the bureau of
prisons regional office in baltimore
right they're all around this conference
room table and i go in i sit down and
one of them says kiriakou we are this
close to violating you you're going to
go right back to prison i go why what
did i do
he goes you haven't taken a single one
of the mandatory classes
and i'm so proud of my response i still
chuckle when i think about it i go in
all seriousness i go
did you ever see that episode of the
simpsons
where homer has to take a parenting
class
and he goes to the parenting class he's
a little bit late so when he walks in
the instructor's saying
put a garbage can lid on the garbage can
people i can't stress that enough
is that what you're going to teach me in
your class
to put a garbage can lid on the garbage
can or how to write a resume
or how to balance a checkbook because i
don't need your classes
he goes step outside
so i step outside i'm out there for like
45 minutes
i go back in he goes
all right you don't have to take any of
the classes and i said thank you and
another thing i want to drive
it took me two hours to get here today
seven and a half miles i said you guys
are on my back all the time
about getting a job
and then you make me come here three
times a week and it kills two hours
getting here and two hours getting home
and then you can't understand why i
don't have a job so i want my driver's
license back and i want permission to
drive
okay you can have permission to drive i
said thank you and i left like you
morons
you know it's it's one size fits all for
these dopes it's so dumb we have the
dumbest
freaking criminal justice system i think
i think we have the most people in
prison per capita than any other country
by far we have four percent
of the world's population
and 25 of the world's prison population
yeah it's ridiculous ridiculous now are
you doing a podcast now or are you doing
you're doing some sort of daily show
yeah i've got a daily radio show a radio
show a terrestrial show in washington um
it's uh every day from 12 to two okay
and i've got
three syndicated columns now one for
consortium news one for covert action
magazine
and one for
the sheer post at the university of
southern california
and then i started something that i'm
i'm really
pleased with it's a new social media
platform called pan quake
and
pan quake is is unlike any other social
media platform you've ever heard of
uh first of all it's utterly completely
transparent
even the code is transparent
so
there are no
algorithms there's nothing that's going
to steer you to
one line of thought or to another or to
follow this guy or to not follow that
guy utterly completely open
it is based in
iceland
so freedom of speech is of the utmost
importance
and uh you know frankly the fbi doesn't
have any subpoena authority or seizure
authority in iceland so that makes it
nicer too
it's blockchain based and um
it's completely and totally financed by
um crowdfunding small donations five ten
fifty bucks
they've repeatedly turned down
major money investors repeatedly
including one who's a household name
and so um yeah it it's something i'm
proud to be is it similar to twitter or
instagram or twitter yes
i'm smiling because
it we try not to say the word twitter oh
okay just because
it's heresy there are yeah are there our
big competition the the big gorilla
800-pound gorilla yeah um but yeah it's
it's
twitter without the algorithms and with
transparency okay yeah that's very
fascinating it's panquake.com
okay
yeah the uh didn't something happen
recently with consortium yes news what
happened with them
yeah so
um
paypal froze consortium that's what it
was that's what it was and not only did
they freeze the account they seized the
9 300 we had in the account on payday no
less um
they wouldn't tell us why
and so the the uh executive editor joe
lauria was able to get through to a
human being at uh paypal he's like why
did you guys do this oh you've all you
violated our terms of agreement
he's like what what violation well there
was no violation and they finally
admitted that there was nobody who
complained they just did this on their
own and finally they admitted that
we weren't
anti-russia enough in our editorials
you weren't anti-russia enough can you
imagine that who said this
paypal paypal
yep so we um
all of us who write for for consortium
news wrote about this and published in
other outlets to try to spread the word
as as widely as we could
and you know we've got i'm on the board
of consortium news we've got people like
chris hedges who's a pulitzer prize
winner we have an academy
award-nominated documentary producer
we've got like legit people these aren't
nuts lunatics you know who dabble in cue
anon these are legitimate people
respected in their fields
and so uh we we put out the word that
not only did they did they uh freeze the
account but they seized all of our money
and we said we're going to join this uh
class action suit that's already been
filed against
uh paypal in the northern district of
california and as soon as we said that
we were going to join the class-action
suit they released all of our money back
to us
wow but they told us that we're
permanently banned from paypal
that's so [__] bonkers man that's
crazy that's so bonkers you weren't
anti-russian enough yeah
and you know one of the reasons why i
love writing for consortium news i
actually work for the russians right i
my show is with the sputnik network but
one of the things that i insisted when
they offered me this job was language in
my contract saying that i can
talk about any issue that i want to talk
about and i can criticize any person
that i want to criticize including
vladimir putin and on the that was your
agreement with sputnik with sputnik and
for people who don't know explain what
sputnik is sputnik is the russian
government's official radio network okay
so it's like uh voice of america
okay for us okay so on the day of the
russian invasion the way i opened my
show is i said i unreservedly condemn
the russian invasion of ukraine i
believe this is a violation of
international law it's a violation of
human rights and i urge the russian
military to withdraw immediately that's
how i open the show
and
i have guests on that criticize the
russians i have guests on that criticize
the ukrainians and when i write
including for consortium news i say
i unreservedly oppose the russian
invasion of ukraine but i understand why
they did it
right two different things
you know war is a bad thing right we
should let the diplomats do their jobs
and and try to prevent war every time
that we can but i understand why the
russians felt they needed to cross the
border that doesn't mean i like it or
agree with it it's just that i
understand it right and they were like
oh no no and they and sputnik aired all
airs all this stuff even if it goes
against the government's narrative yeah
because everything that you hear
anywhere is that that's not what it's
like in russia right everything in
russia is tailored to what the
government wants you to hear
it's all propaganda cnn did a story
about my show a couple of weeks ago and
they said that i was weakening democracy
can you imagine you were weakening
in the united states because i'm a
former cia officer
i should be standing up for my country
not working for the russians and i said
yeah i said to this nick whatever's name
was the reporter i said are you gonna
put food on my table are you gonna put
my kids through college yeah where was
cnn when i got out of prison and i
needed a helping hand
so don't tell me about weakening
democracy well that's weird because cnn
hires i think more ex-pentagon officials
exactly any other any other company they
pay the last four cia officials are
either at
or cia directors are at either cnn or
msnbc right
yeah what is what do you think about
that about all these ex-pentagon
officials cia lists
scandalous where's the where's the
separation
you know it's like cnn msnbc and fox
same thing they're all just adjuncts of
the national security state
it's crazy
that's so wild
so [__] wild
well man i don't know i don't know what
the answer is but that seems
bonkers that that's the world we live in
yes it's been a real learning lesson
and where so where can people listen to
your daily show again
uh
almost nowhere we've been banned from
youtube
itunes i heart radio spreaker spotify
and tune in what yeah you've been banned
from i'm modified i'm weakening
democracy
how the frick did you get banned from
every single platform so the only way to
listen to it now is at sputniknews.com
we went from 38 000 daily listeners to
500.
no [__] way yep
that's crazy totally [__] wise 38 to
which is what they wanted to do oh
my they don't want anybody who has an
alternative viewpoint otherwise
democracy might get weakened
because what are you saying what what
are you saying to weaken democracy what
specifically are they pointing to i can
tell you um every thursday i have a
30-minute segment called criminal
injustice
and i have a journalist
who focuses on criminal justice issues
and a guy who's the head of a group
called um the human rights defense
center they publish prison legal news
and criminal legal news magazines
and so we talk every week for 30 minutes
about crooked judges crooked prosecutors
the death penalty cops getting arrested
for you know raping prisoners and
selling drugs and stuff like that
wow
and i get it all out of the washington
post the new york times
but that's weakening democracy
holy [__]
[Music]
well this episode's definitely going to
get banned from youtube
[Laughter]
oh my god you know a funny thing too is
everybody at the station on twitter they
got this tag that says russian russian
sponsored media right
i have 50 000 twitter followers and i
don't i don't have a tag i don't know
why knock on wood i don't want one i'm
not russian sponsored media
explain this tag this tag is implemented
by twitter yeah there's a there's so
twitter put a flag on these accounts
that says it's a russian every single
one of my colleagues i'm gonna show you
oops maybe he can pull it up on the tv
on the screen sure what's one of the
colleagues names uh lee stranahan lee
stranahan on twitter yeah lee stranahan
okay
i gotta see this yeah
because i know that russia i know that
uh i know that twitter implemented um
tags on posts that are created by
automated bots
right i had this guy out here the other
day who uh he has a bot that poses
russian state-affiliated media
so he didn't put that on there no sir
twitter did
about a week after the russians invaded
ukraine
well click on that what does that go to
oh i didn't even know you could click on
it about government and state-affiliated
media account labels on twitter labels
on state-affiliated accounts provide
additional context about accounts that
are controlled by certain official
representatives of government state
affiliate
still state affiliated media entities
and individuals associated with those
entities the label appears on the
profile page of a relevant twitter
account wow
look and they put the flag
these labels include a small icon of a
flag to signal the account's status
oh
man
that's pretty [__] crazy i never knew
about this
terrible i never knew about this
go back to his uh profile again
russian state affiliated media with the
russian flag now did he put so they he
didn't put the [__] russian flag now
twitter put the russian flag
because you know one of the weird things
about people on twitter is like i always
become suspicious of somebody on twitter
when they have the [__] american flag
emoji next to their name right
right you think they're some sort of
like either they're right wing or
they're just some sort of [__]
antagonist on twitter yes who's just
trying to get attention you know what i
mean yes like a provocateur agreed
agreed that's [__] bananas
i don't know how i feel about that yeah
i don't like it i didn't know that was a
thing i wonder what elon will do about
that if he gets twitter yeah good
question
good question
jesus and that's another thing about
elon is he is a lot of his businesses
are relying on federal grants and
federal money a lot
he didn't become the world's richest man
by accident right
the american government spacex launches
all these government military satellites
into space i know that tesla is is super
reliant on federal funding
yep
but nobody i haven't heard anything
about that
i mean i don't not that i don't think it
would be a bad thing for elon to buy
twitter but it's just an interesting i
hope he i hope he cleans the place up i
really do
wow artist john thank you again where
can people follow you again where can
people find your books uh the books are
all on amazon okay um i'm at john
kiriakou.com
k-i-r-i-a-k-o-u just the way it sounds
um twitter facebook
all the usual places
awesome well thank you again for
spending your time and coming down here
i i very much appreciate it and i really
enjoyed this conversation thank you
[Music]
you